[Music]
[Applause]
well thank you very much it's a great
pleasure to be here in this massive hall
I can't believe that all of you decided
that coming to talk about the topics
we're going to talk about tonight was
the top priority in your life but but
let's see if we can justify that you
know that might be a good that might be
a good aim see if we could make it
worthwhile
so make your decision correct so you may
know or not that I was on a television
show last night Q&A apparently you know
that some of you anyways I can't say I
enjoyed it really really it's funny you
know like I think as I've got farther
along in doing whatever it is that I
happen to be doing I find those events
more and more stressful I don't know
exactly what it is I think it's the
proclivity of everything everything has
to be mangled in some sense into a
preset format you know and and the
fundamental format really is that
everything has to be political you know
and everything isn't political so that's
not helpful
when you're trying to discuss things
that aren't political and I mean I'm not
complaining about it well I suppose I am
it's just it's it's surprising to me how
how how
how much it how much it takes out of me
say compared to doing an event like this
which I really enjoy doing like I spent
a lot of time preparing and there's a
lot of you and I really want it to go
well and all that but this is this is
much less dreadful haha I guess that's
right and you know and then there's the
strange constraints on format you know
people ask very complex questions and
and then you have a minute to answer and
you know there's something there's
something downright sinful about
answering a really complicated question
in a minute because it sort of suggests
that complex questions have answers that
take one minute and they don't they have
answers that take God sometimes they
take decades sometimes they take
thousands of years you know but of
course I can't expect a television show
to allow for a thousands of years but
but the format itself works against the
kind of thought that's necessary to
actually have discussions that are
necessary and so anyways having said all
that it went it went oh it went all
right I would say there were no nasty
surprises and particularly and it was a
civil discussion whether it was a
productive discussion or not is a
different matter but it wasn't an
unproductive discussion and so that's
something but there was one question
that came up and I thought I would
actually start talking about that
question tonight because I've never been
happy I've been asked this question a
lot and I've never been happy with the
answer that I've given to it and I've
never really been able to exactly get my
I've never been able to figure out
exactly why I haven't been happy with
the question and so I'm gonna try to
answer it properly tonight and then I'm
going to talk more generally about 12
rules about the book
now it's fine this question is directly
relevant to the book and so it should
make for a good lead-in but it'll enable
us to talk about something that I think
is really very much worth talking about
and I hope I can formulate the problem
properly and then formulate the proper
sir at least more coherently than I've
managed its see I have I have this I
followed this rule for a very long time
which I actually found was a Socratic
rule I didn't know this until really
quite recently until I wrote 12 rules
for life Socrates said that he had a
daemon and by which he meant an internal
voice and he said that at all he always
listened to it and then that was what
made him different from other people
that he always listened to this voice
and the voice didn't tell him what to do
he told him what not to do and when the
Delphic Oracle proclaimed that Socrates
was the wisest man in Greece in Athens
and in Greece one of the reasons
Socrates attributed her decision to deem
him the wisest man was because while she
said he knew he knew nothing but he knew
in part that he knew nothing at least in
part because he was always listening to
the voice of his Damon his internal
conscience and then I just found out the
other day that the word democracy comes
from the same root which is really
interesting like I had no idea that that
was the case because what it suggests
it's it's it's it's so fascinating
looking at how words are related to one
another
historically because you find strange
connections between ideas that you would
never imagine and sometimes they're
unbelievably profound and so the basic
what happened historically is that well
so there was a concept of the Socratic
Damon now it was the Damon that Socrates
listened to when he decided that he was
not going to run when the Athenians
decided that they were going to put him
to death the Athenian aristocrats right
because they thought that he was
corrupting the youth by you know talking
to them and telling them the truth and I
suppose that's certainly grounds for
chasing someone out of your town anyways
they gave him plenty of notice because
they didn't really want to kill him they
just wanted to get the old goat the hell
out to some other city where he could
cause trouble there and
his friends were you know making plans
to get to scurry him away from Athens
and he went out consulted his Damon and
it told him not to leave and that was a
big shark to Socrates because of course
he didn't want to die and but yet he had
decided that he was always going to
follow the dictates of the damon and he
so he did something that only a
philosopher would do was reversed his
assumptions he thought oh well I was
afraid of dying and my Damon said stick
around and so I must be wrong it must be
worse to be to risk not following that
internal voice than to risk this form of
death you know which is question you
have to really wrestle with and when his
friend when his friends weren't very
happy about but in any case he didn't
run and we have two good court like
documents attesting to that one written
by someone named Xenophon and the other
by Plato they're very interesting
documents I would highly recommend
reading them they're very short and the
reason one of the reasons I would
recommend reading them apart from the
fact that they're fascinating and and
short is that you also get the sense
from from what Socrates wrote that
because he had lived his life fully you
know no holds barred in some sense that
he could let it go when the time came
and and that's an interesting thing you
know because well it's a question I
think that we all wrestle with we should
is like well is there a purpose to our
life and well that's a hard question and
then if there is a purpose well how is
it expressed and then if there is a
purpose and our lives are truncated as
they are by death then how can that
purpose have significance and those are
hard questions but Socrates experience
seemed to be that he had lived enough in
his life so that when push came to shove
which it certainly did he was able to
gracefully let it go
and that's
and you know he attested to that with
his death and and and that's fairly
convincing you know I mean that's a
fairly convincing argument and it's one
that I find well it's hard to tell if I
find it exactly credible but I don't
find it incredible I mean I certainly
have noticed that as I've got older and
I've done things various what would you
say accomplished isn't exactly the right
word I've participated in many things
that I'm pleased to have participated in
them but wouldn't necessarily go back
and participate in them again it's sort
of as if when you do something and you
finish it it's as if it's done you don't
have to do it again and maybe it's
possible who knows that if you finish
your life whatever that might mean if
you exhaust your life then then that's
enough life you know that you've had
enough and I mean that doesn't mean that
I try not to keep myself healthy and
that I want to die tomorrow it doesn't
mean any of that I'm trying to stick
around as long as I can but but but
there's still that that that curiosity
about the relationship between life and
mortality and and the possibility that a
life well-lived exhausts itself in some
fundamental sense so that you can be
satisfied let's say with with what you
with what you were there is some
psychological evidence that bears on
this if you ask people what they regret
especially as they get older what they
generally port is things not done so
they don't regret so much mistakes
they've made although of course people
obviously regret mistakes they've made
as well so they don't exactly regret
sins of commission right errors that
they've actively made they they miss
they they torment themselves for
opportunities that had presented
themselves
that they did not let's say exploit or
engage in and I think that's worth
thinking about too because one thing
that I have become convinced about with
regards to human consciousness which i
think is equivalent to the spark of
divinity in some sense that our
fundamental stories insists as being
placed within us is that human
consciousness is that faculty that
confronts potential itself I think
there's good neurological evidence for
this by the way for those of you who are
scientifically minded because we build
circuits within us for habitual action
that we've practiced many times that
seem to run in a very deterministic
fashion and we are a strange combination
of deterministic and non-deterministic
as far as I can tell but what our
consciousness seems to be for is to
encounter those things that we have not
yet encountered and those things that we
have not yet encountered seem to me to
be those things that have not yet been
brought into being and so you could say
that what our consciousness is for is
for the encounter with potential you
know that our consciousness is further
it's not for the past it's not even for
the present it's to transform the future
into the present and and really that
that's what our consciousness does when
you wake up in the morning you have a
new day ahead of you and the day could
take you in very many directions and and
the weeks and the years all of that can
take you in very many directions and you
have some apprehension about what those
directions might be you have some
apprehension about what role your
choices might make in transforming that
potential into one form of actuality or
another I mean you certainly know that
there are dreadful mistakes that you
might be very tempted to make that would
produce all manner of Hell around you
and still be tempted to do it it seems
like it's sitting there right in front
of you as a possibility you also know
that you know you could haul yourself up
out of bed and attend to your duties and
do the sorts of things that you're
supposed to
a few things right that day and that
weekend that likely things would at
least not be worse and they would
probably be better and I believe that I
do believe that I don't understand how
this can be the case I don't understand
how it is that consciousness
consciousness can function in that way
because I think to understand that we
would have to understand what it means
for the future to be only potential
rather than actuality and who the hell
understands that I mean no one and then
we'd have to understand how it is that
our conscious choices and our conscious
ethical choices transform that
potentiality into actuality into reality
into the present in the past and we
certainly but we certainly act as if we
believe that that's what we do we
upgrade ourselves for example when we do
a bad job of it we're upset with our
children and those we love if we don't
believe that they're living up to their
potential we're guilty and ashamed when
we make choices that we feel are
inappropriate we understand to some
degree that the manner in which time
lays itself out has something to do with
the ethics of our choice and again I
would say that's a very deep idea I
think it's a I think it's I think it's
the most true idea I know that's very
emphasized that idea emphasized in
ancient religious stories such as those
that are outlined in Genesis or in
Genesis with it's strange insistence
that you know God is that which brings
order out of chaos
formless potential generates the world
out of formless potential and that were
somehow made in that image which which
seems to me to be the case and at the
proper way by the way to go about acting
in that image is to act in relationship
to the potential that confronts you with
truth and with courage with careful
articulation that's the logos and that
if you do that then what you bring forth
is is good so it
those are all background ideas that are
associated with 12 rules for life and
they have a bearing on this question
that I want to answer tonight and so I'm
going to sit I have some notes which I
don't usually use about I'm gonna use
them tonight because I haven't got
everything about this particular notion
memorized in some sense yet because I'm
still working it out but that should
work out okay so we'll see we'll see
what happens
so yeah yeah well good so Windows work
that's always good seeing I've seen it
not work sometimes when Bill Gates
demonstrates it and that's that's got to
be very very embarrassing although I
would say you know all things considered
he seems to have done quite well all
right so here's here's the question that
came up last night and this is a strange
question for what is essentially a
political show near the end a gentleman
on videotape came up and and he
discussed the topic of human dignity not
it's not a topic you hear a lot about
there's a lot of topics that are sort of
related to human beings that you don't
hear a lot about anymore you don't hear
a lot about nobility you don't hear a
lot about endurance let's say stalwart
Ness courage dignity those aren't values
that we discuss much responsibility
being another one which is one I'm quite
thrilled about all things considered
because I think it's the pathway to
meaning itself but so hit his was the
topic of human dignity and he asked us a
question do you believe in God and then
he said as a Catholic I don't see any
other way that we can have a universe
with dignity and so I'm not so concerned
about the second part of his commentary
although I might get to that but the
first part do you believe in God
is a question that's been leveled at me
many times and I'm going to come other
people on the panel and I'm going to
just review what they said briefly and
then I'm going to talk about what I said
and then I'm going to fix what I said I
hope so that it's better at least that's
the plan
so Terry Butler who's was a laborer is a
labor front bencher said I'm agnostic
people are inherently valuable because
they are people
and no that doesn't work out very it's
it's it's um it's one of those
one-minute answers except it's actually
only ten seconds because you can you can
make the opposite argument and people do
all the time you know like the Club of
Rome for example which was an
organization in Rome
logically enough formed in the 60s it
was very much concerned about the
terribly detrimental effect that human
beings were having on the planet and I
believe it was one of the Club of Rome
members who coined the idea and and if
it wasn't it was someone who was
thinking exactly the same way so works
out either way that human beings were
something approximating a cancer on the
planet you know because of all the
terrible things we were doing
ecologically and so forth that was back
when people believed we were going to
over populate the planet to such a
degree by the year 2000 that there would
be widespread privation and starvation
which by the way if you haven't noticed
there isn't and and you know if you look
at the terrible things that people do
apart from the despoiling of the natural
environment let's say there's all the
you know malevolence that's associated
with human interactions and also human
social systems and it isn't so obvious
as a consequence of that that you can
make a straightforward case that human
beings are inherently valuable merely
because they're human beings because you
can eat make an equally logical case
from first principles that they're
inherently well destructive or that they
should be perhaps limited in their
ability to procreate or that they are a
catastrophe for the planet as a whole
or that our entire history is nothing
but a sequence of on what would you call
unrequited malevolence and that people
generally can't be trusted and so I
don't find that answer particularly
satisfying I think it's a it's a it's
it's just self referential people are
inherently valuable because they're
people it's like well you don't really
get anywhere with an answer like that so
so she's agnostic and and then and but
then she has this idea
despite her agnosticism that you can
make the case a priori with nothing but
resummon heritable and seems to me that
that requires a little more depth and a
little more explanation for it to
actually be convincing you know it's
like it's not obvious to me that people
themselves think that they're valuable
all the time often they don't think that
at all they don't certainly don't think
that often when they're depressed they
certainly don't think that when they're
suicidal they don't really think that
when they're ashamed or guilty or
frustrated or disappointed or angry or
waking up at 3:00 in the morning and
tormenting themselves with their
consciences they don't necessarily think
that when they're fighting with their
family or when they're upset at work or
you know when things go wrong in life
and so it's not so bloody obvious that
people are inherently valuable and and
then you might also notice that it's
kind of easy to think that some people
are more valuable than others
sort of like an animal farm you know
where the animals were all equal except
that some animals were more equal than
others
but it's very easy for human beings to
think that about other human beings
because no matter where you look in
human societies there are rank orders of
value right in in any hierarchy that we
produce that's associated with some
ability we find that some people are so
much better at whatever it is that
they're doing that it's an absolute
miracle and most people are absolutely
dreadful at it and so you know if you
were thinking about inherent value as
something associated with something with
with an approximation of skill or
competence then it wouldn't be obvious
from the structure of the world that
people were inherently valuable in that
manner either because there's such a
rank order difference in our ability to
do things you know and you might say
well that kind of averages out across
things but I don't think that's a very
strong argument either so so it's not
it's bloody well not obvious I'll tell
you it's not obvious where this idea
that people are inherently valuable came
from that's a tough one
you know an end and in and in and in
aristocratic states or or tyrannical
states it's certainly not obvious at all
that there's any acceptance of the
notion that people are inherently
valuable it's like there's no necessary
presumption of innocence for example and
you don't have any sovereign right to
your own destiny like you're not granted
the rights not granted because that's
the wrong way of thinking about it your
rights as a sovereign individual who has
the responsibility and the capability to
determine the destiny of the state
itself don't exist that doesn't exist as
a concept and so I don't see that
there's anything there that speaks of
inherent value either so it's by no
means an obvious concept in fact I think
it's one of the least obvious concepts
that human beings have ever come up with
that each of us in some strange manner
is is is to be attributed some divine
spark let's say that makes us equal in
some fundamental way before God you know
before the reality of the universe
itself
even in relationship to our own laws I
mean if you want a miracle for an idea
that's that's I can't think of one
that's that's more unlikely than that so
I've been puzzling over that for a very
long time because I cannot understand
why in the world that idea ever came to
be or how in the world we ever agreed to
act as if it was true it's really
something and we should let that go with
we let that idea go to our great peril
it's a fundamental remarkable
fundamental idea and what's so
interesting about it too is that once
you have that idea weird as it is and
improbable as it is and you start to
organize your social relationships in
accordance with it well then they work
you know so my rule two is treat
yourself as if you're someone
responsible for helping and it's sort of
predicated on the idea that regardless
of your inadequacies and your
malevolence which
you know I'm sure you have many
inadequacies and no shortage of
malevolence just like everyone else
regardless of that you have a moral
obligation so that would be a
responsibility to assume that despite
all evidence that there's actually
something of intrinsic worth about you
and that as a consequence you're
duty-bound to treat yourself like that
is true and then it turns out that if
you do that well then your life gets
better and and I don't mean happier
exactly although I would say it gets
happier I mean it gets richer and more
meaningful and deeper and and more
worthwhile and and you become more
educated and you become wiser and and
and you treat yourself with more respect
and you're a better model for other
people and you're a better father or a
better sister or better mother whatever
it happens to be it's and you're less
ridden by that guilt that that gnaws at
you and shame that's there otherwise
saying you're not what you could be
you're not what you could be and that's
a hell of a voice to get rid of and it's
certainly not one that's easy to ignore
so that's a pretty good that that idea
that there's something divine let's say
that resides within you of ultimate
worth even as a philosophical statement
or a psychological statement rather than
a metaphysical statement it seems to be
a precondition for establishing properly
harmonious relationships with yourself
and that's that's man that's we're
thinking about a lot you know that you
have because you think you couldn't
think that in some sense you just own
yourself you know because people do kind
of make that claim especially when
they're trying to justify for example
their right to suicide but you know it's
your life it's your body you're yours to
do what you will with and if that was
true well then it would seem to me that
life would be a lot more straightforward
because you would just tell yourself
things that you would instantly obey and
believe so first of all you tell
yourself all the things that you were
going to do and then you just run off
and do them which you don't or
obviously because it's much more
difficult at that and then you'd also
say well enough of the guilt and the
shame and the negative emotion and the
disillusionment and the vengefulness and
all those things that make life hard has
spread the self-recrimination it's like
what the hell do we need that for
and if we're our masters of our own
destiny and owners of our own fate and
why can't we just command to ourselves
that that be dispensed with and like
that doesn't work I've never seen
anybody able to do that so I mean you
can fool yourself for very brief periods
of time into thinking that that might
work but but it doesn't work and that's
strange begin that this is one of the
reasons I love the psychoanalyst say
because they were really the people
apart from the religious types who
figured out that whatever you are you're
not a unitary spirit that's under your
own Dominion you know you're something
like a loose unity of a multiplicity of
spirits many of which are doing their
own thing which you're striving to bring
into some form of unity but even that
unity isn't something that's under your
control in any real sense it's it's a
unity that has its own nature that you
have to exist in relationship to and I
would also say that that's one of the
things that keeps people people's feet
firmly on the ground because otherwise
you it's easy to become egotistical and
narcissistic you know if you if you
think that you're the center of your own
being you know in some fundamental sense
then you're only what you're only
beholding to yourself you're sort of a
self created creature perhaps you could
think about it that way but it doesn't
work like that it's like the ideal that
constitutes the unity that you might
become then sort of manifests itself as
something that you could strive toward
but aren't and it it it also serves as a
judge it's the thing that keeps you up
at night saying you know there's some
things you're just not attending to and
you should get at it because life is
short and there's no shortage of trouble
that you might end up in and a wise
person would attend to the dictates of
conscience and and lay out his actions
in the world according to what he knows
to be true and correct and that is how
people think and it isn't obvious that
we why we think that way that this is
part of the reason that it seems to me
so obvious that we have a religious
instinct because I can't think of what
else you would possibly call that other
than a religious instinct you know
Nietzsche when he proclaimed the death
of God which which by the way was no
triumphant Proclamation because he also
mentioned that we would never find
enough water to wash away the blood
which was his what would you call it
prognostication for the 20th century and
a very accurate one at that he believed
that we would in some sense have to
become as gods
you know in ourselves in order to
replace what we had lost he thought that
that the collapse of the judeo-christian
structure would be absolutely
catastrophic for the West and I believe
that he was correct and that the way out
of that would be that we would have to
create our own values we'd have to take
the place of what was once let's say
externalized and divine on to ourselves
and you know it's a hell of a theory and
and it's not and Nietzsche is not an
easy person to criticize because you you
have to do a lot of reading before you
find someone who's 1/10 as smart as
Nietzsche he has this funny line about
his books
it's really quite comical he said takes
most writers a whole book to write what
I can write in a sentence then he said
no they can't even manage it in a book
and that's actually true I mean if you
read Nietzsche be one good and evil for
example you see that that that his his
thought is so powerful that it's really
it's it's it's really a kind of miracle
what what the psychoanalyst realized
though this was particularly Jung's
contribution I would say Carl Jung's
contribution he was a great student of
Nietzsche a real admirer of Nietzsche
and really someone who is trying to
solve the problem that need
she had put forward which was well our
underlying metaphysics our religious
structure had collapsed and that was the
story upon which our until entire
culture was based for better or worse it
had collapsed and we needed to do
something about that and we were doing
various things we were turning to
fascism let's say or we were turning to
communism both ideological replacements
for more fundamental religious beliefs
but that Nietzsche's suggestion that we
turn to ourselves to extract out our own
values to create our own values let me
let me be more accurate about that
happened to be untrue because we weren't
the sort of creatures who were actually
capable of doing that and that's a it's
such what's one of the reasons I love
Jung and his is biological take in some
sense towards human beings because you
know firmly believed and I think all of
the evidence supports him believed that
human beings actually had a nature you
know that that we that we weren't merely
social constructions which we certainly
aren't despite what the social
constructionist insist upon forcing us
to think increasingly through
legislative means and that we had to
wrestle with what it was that we were
you know even though we're we're our own
creatures in some sense we also have to
wrestle with our intrinsic nature and
and we know about we know that about the
nature part of that more and more I mean
we know more about our neural circuitry
for example we know that there's a
circuit for rage and there's a circuit
for fear and there's a there's a
biological system for jealousy and
there's a system for altruism and
there's a circuit for play and there's
another one for pleasure and there's a
complex circuit for negative emotion
pain and anxiety and frustration and
disappointment guilt and shame and we
know that human beings share that
motivational structure not only with all
other human beings but with certainly
with all mammals and almost all animals
and so that bile of a biological
component of us is unbelievably
right it's its mill tens of millions
hundreds of millions and even and even
billions of years old I read an
interesting paper just the other day you
know I tend to talk about lobsters more
than the average person and one of the
points I made in twelve rules for life
was that our neural chemistry at least
some of it is so similar it's been
conserved so completely throughout the
immense duration of evolution hundreds
of millions of years that lobsters like
human beings appear to become the
lobster equivalent of depressed if they
suffer a hierarchy defeat and that if
you give them chemicals that are roughly
analogous to human antidepressants it
perks them right back up their posture
improves and they'll go off and fight
and you know when I first discovered
that it just well it just it just blew
me away I never recovered from it I
thought my god really that the continent
is 350 million years of continuity in in
in the structure of those systems and
you know we know the serotonin system
which is the system I'm talking about
does govern your observation of where
you sit in a social hierarchy like it
does for many many animal species and as
one consequence of that regulates your
emotion so that if it sees that you're a
relatively high status creature in your
local environment then it tends to allow
you to feel more positive emotion and
less negative emotion and if it sees you
as a low status creature in your local
comparative environment that it does the
opposite it overwhelms you with negative
emotion and suppresses positive emotion
and so you know and that's really bad no
one likes that it's it's it's
fundamentally there's really nothing
worse that can happen to you than that
to have those emotions re re adjusted in
that manner so that the incentive reward
and the motivation and the positive
emotion vanishes from your life so
there's nothing to be enthusiastic or
excited about and all of the negative
emotions pain disappointment frustration
grief all of those terrible negative
emotions are
Mendeley magnified no one wants that
it's the it's the last thing you want
perhaps it's the last thing you want and
you know that's partly why people are
very let's call it what would you say
they're tightly they're willing to fight
for their position in their status
hierarchy and even for the existence of
the hierarchies themselves so anyways it
is the case that human beings have a
nature and and we have to contend with
that nature and so we can't just create
our own values and and what what young
especially you Freud started it but
especially you believed that well in
some sense what had happened was that we
had lost the externalized religious
narrative that had been projected by our
imagination out onto the world you know
you think about the the constellations
and and and the names of the
constellations and the idea that the
skies were populated by gods you know
that was an externalization of our
imagination right projected out into the
world we were seeing the world through
our imagination and which is exactly how
we do see the world and as we proceed
we're better able to distinguish let's
say what's imagination from what
subjective world but that doesn't mean
the imagination disappears or that it's
without value because the imagination is
part of what helps us let's say confront
the future because we do that with our
imagination and to compose things in
impossibility before we realize them in
actuality so for young the world of gods
just collapsed within back into the
imagination and it was into the
imagination that we had to go again to
discover what we had lost to discover
these these lost values and that's akin
in some sense I suppose to rescuing your
father from the belly of the whale a
very brilliant brilliant
toward of intellectual tour-de-force to
to manage that supposition especially
back when back when he did it and I
think I see no evidence whatsoever that
he was wrong
given as I said our radical inability to
command
ourselves as
we are our own in some fundamental way
we seem subject to now I'm we seem
subject to intractable moral laws and
I'm not trying to make a case for the
accuracy of those laws necessarily or
for their metaphysical origin but I am
trying to make a case for their
psychological and phenomenological
reality you definitely experience them
in so far as you suffer let's say that
from from them from them pricks and
arrows of your own conscience and I
doubt if there's a single person in this
room who doesn't regularly suffer in
that manner and some of you suffer like
that virtually all the time when you
know which can also be a problem in any
case you know it's it's it's interesting
to note that we're not exactly masters
in our own houses and that's that's how
such a interesting thing to note because
you think well if we're not masters in
our own houses well what is it is it
just is it just a chaotic internal
structure is it merely the voice of
nature and nature's various instinctual
subsystems that doesn't seem to be
correct because we do integrate them
into something approximating a unity
there's more than just the basics of
nature we have language we have
communication we have culture we build
up above nature something that's more
than nature but we're still beholden to
it the question is well what are we
beholden to what is this that we're
beholding to and socially politically
and individually that we cannot escape
from well so that's part of the question
do you believe in God well this part of
the answer actually and you know it's no
bleak answer but the first thing I'm
trying to say is try controlling
yourself try acting as if you're the
fundamental source of your own values
independent of any what would you call a
transcendent ethical structure to see if
you can do that but try it for a week
try it for a month
I've never met anybody that could do it
now not even for a moment I mean I don't
know how many of you have read
Dostoyevsky
and punishment but I would highly
recommend that if you're interested in
this sort of thing because it's the
definitive study of this idea because in
crime and punishment the protagonist
commits the perfect murder and he has
his reasons for it and more and many
reasons because dusty husky didn't mess
around when he wanted to give someone
reasons he gave them reasons and
Raskolnikov the main character had
reasons for murder and then he commits
his murder and he gets away with it but
things don't go well for a Skolnick off
because one of the things he finds out
is that the risk alna carve that you
were before you committed the murder is
not the same as the risk all in the club
as you are after you've committed the
murder and there's a dividing line there
that you don't it's like the red pill I
guess right it's like it that's the
matrix correct the red pill and once
there's certain actions once you take
them there's no going back and so that's
what crime and punishment is about and
risk Olenick off tortures himself to
death well not literally but
metaphysically psychologically because
he cannot tolerate breaking the great
moral code and so it's what's a great
book it's truly a great book and and
it's also extraordinarily like it's a
it's a it's a it's a murder mystery
thriller as well as being a deep
philosophical book so if you're in the
mood for you know a murder mystery
thriller that's also a deep
philosophical book then that's the one
for you so now one of the other speakers
on the panel van Badham who who who
described was described not by me as a
writer activist and Twitter Queen which
is I think like being the Red Queen in
in Ellis in Wunderland something like
that I went on her Twitter site today to
find out how many followers she has but
apparently I'm not one of them because
I'm blocked
and it kind of surprises me because I
didn't know that I'd ever tried to
follow her but anyways she said and this
was interesting she said I'm a Christian
and a Marxist and I thought no you can
only be a Christian and a Marxist if you
well there's a couple of ways one is one
is that you just want to be all things
that are good at once regardless of
their internal contradictions and so
that would be one reason and another
reason would be that you don't know
anything about Christianity or Marxism
and and and then the next would be that
you're just compartmentalized you know
like there's this idea that people can't
hold 2 contradictory thoughts in their
mind at the same time well that idea was
formulated by someone who who's never
met a human being because you can hold
like 50 contradictory thoughts in your
head at the same time as you know
whenever you argue with someone that you
love because you love them and maybe you
even like them but you also hate them
and you wish that you could just crush
them right there and then and so like
that's a lot of contradictory ideas and
that's probably only like half the
contradictory ideas that are running
through your mind at the moment you know
so man you're so full of contradictions
that it's just beyond belief and the
only time I mean I know this because I
read undergraduate essays and what's
what's interesting about undergraduate
essays is it's so interesting because
the undergraduate will make a claim in
paragraph one and then in paragraph
seven will make the opposite claim and
they won't notice that they're
intellectually and commensurate and you
know that might happen 30 times in the
essay and and the reason that that that
works is because well they haven't been
called on paradoxes but also because
they haven't had to live the paradoxes
through because you
the only straight note you thought when
you have like impulse a and impulse B
and they conflict at the same time right
and you can either do one or the other
but not both you know if it's a today
and B tomorrow well then you can be you
can hold those ideas simultaneously but
if it's a or B right now then you have
to decide is a more important or is B
more important you have to put them in a
hierarchy and then you have to act them
out and you have to see what happens and
so then you find out if you're full of
contradictions and part of the way that
you iron out your contradictions which
is very very hard to do is that you Walt
and you do a whole bunch of things in
the world like Socrates did you go you
have your adventure in the world and you
put your ideas to the test and those
that work out in a paradoxical or
counterproductive manner you dispense
with or put lower on the priority list
or something like that and that's how
you discover that you know you can't
hold in commensurate views
simultaneously Carl Jung said that
something like paradoxical views that
are not made conscious will be played
out in the world as fate and that's
really worth thinking about too so if
you have your let's call it your typical
negative experience you know this thing
that just keeps seems to just keep
happening to you bad luck let's call it
it's highly probable that there's a set
of ideas that are occupying you
preoccupying you possessing you that are
driving you in this direction
continually and that you you can't or
won't work out the contradiction and as
a consequence you know maybe you think
every woman is your mother and you
haven't noticed that you think that and
that that you know and it is something
that people think because women are
mothers are women and it's not a bad
initial template but you know you gotta
you gotta modify it to some degree and
you know if that's an unconscious idea
that you have and you continue to play
it out you may run into your continual
habitual negative experience with women
and you wonder what the hell is wrong
with women but there it isn't the women
that has the problem it's you and and
you know if you run into problems with
women all the time
then it's highly probable that the
problem is you so not always but
generally so let's go into this Marxist
and Christian idea here just for a
minute so Oh we'll start with let's
start with some of the ideas of Marx
well Marx believed that people were
basically socially constructed so that
we were blank slates and that whatever
our nature was was given to us
essentially by our surroundings but even
more importantly by our social class
right because Marx was a theorist of
social class and believed that the
primary dispute let's say the primary
motivator of human history the primary
driver of human history was something
like the rich versus the poor the Mersey
versus the proletariat and that was a
consequence of your social upbringing
and that your group identity was
paramount
okay so there's nothing about that it's
vaguely Christian that's not how the
Christian worldview works know how the
judeo-christian worldview works because
in that world you you're fundamentally
an individual your nature is
fundamentally attributable to you by God
you're fundamentally responsible to God
and your and and history itself is
something like the playing out of your
relationship to the transcendent so
those things aren't even those aren't
the same they're not commensurate you
can't believe both of them at the same
time Marxism is a materialistic
philosophy it's predicated on the idea
that essentially an idea that
Dostoyevsky criticized in great depth
was that if you just made people rich
enough let's say if you deprived them of
their privation if you equalize their
economic status let's say that the
Utopia would come to light upon earth
and you know I I have a certain amount
of sympathy for a view point like that
because you know who likes starvation
and
and misery you know there's nothing
positive to be said about that but I
think Dostoyevsky was right too in his
criticism of Marxism although he wasn't
directly aiming this at Marx in notes
from underground where he noted that you
know if you gave people what they wanted
in terms of let's say bread and circuses
they had as he said nothing to do but
eat cakes and busy themselves with the
continuation of the species which is
kind of a nice phrase that the first
thing they would do is take a hammer and
smash things just so that something
improbable and strange would happen just
so that we could have our way you know
and it's kind of a recapitulation of the
idea of original sin in in Dostoyevsky
subtle manner is that were the sorts of
creatures that you know what did he say
we're ungrateful that's the thing that
primarily distinguishes us from animals
is we're ungrateful and that we can
curse that was what he thought made us
different than animals and that if even
if we got what we wanted materially that
wouldn't satisfy us because we're not
the sorts of creatures that can be
satisfied with material possessions
let's err material comfort because it
isn't even obvious that we're after
comfort I mean what do you want you want
you want to just lay in a feather bed
and eat peeled grapes all day I mean
maybe for an hour or so that might not
be a bad idea but you know it's gonna
get dull pretty quick you're gonna go
out looking for trouble and and it's
certainly possible that the more
material resources and the easier they
were to get that you have at your
disposal the more creative ways you're
going to find to cause yourself trouble
when you go out and look for trouble and
so and that's a testament to the human
spirit and Dostoevsky knew this is like
well whatever we're here for it isn't
the Utopia of equal material
distribution that that's not we're not
we're not we're not looking to be fed
and asleep you know and I don't know
what it is that we're looking for god
only knows maybe what we're looking for
is to continually keep looking something
like that I mean that's the sorts of
creatures that we are but but the but
the materialist philosophy is that well
if you just prove
I did for people economically problem
over and no wrong I mean most of you are
as given that you're you know you're
going to be ill in one way or another
and that you're still subject to
mortality and and all of the terrible
natural limitations that human beings
are characterized by your mode is well
off as you're gonna get you know the
economic data already show that once you
have enough money so that bill
collectors aren't chasing you which
basically puts you say at the kind of in
the upper reaches of the working class
or maybe the lower end of the middle
class something like that that
additional money has absolutely no
effect whatsoever on your self-reported
well-being which is something like a
combination of positive emotion and
absence of negative emotion so you might
like to think that you know if you were
rich your life would be better and maybe
it would be somewhat better but it
wouldn't be as much better as you might
hope and that's because you'd still have
most of the problems that people have
you know you still maybe wouldn't get
along with your sister and you'd still
get divorced and maybe you'd even be
more likely to and there'd still be
illness as that would be set you you'd
be able to deal with them perhaps with
some degree a more urgency but and you'd
still have the problem with what the
hell your life is for and what you're
doing on the planet and how to conduct
yourself in the proper way and so so we
don't want to be too naive about
materialism even though we don't want to
be ungrateful for its advantages Marx
also believed while I said this already
that you know history was basically
characterized by the war of
socioeconomic groups that's being
transformed more recently into the war
of identity groups which is the same
damn thing and it's the same old wolf in
new sheep's clothing as far as I'm
concerned that you know the best way to
conceptualize human beings is well I
don't know whatever your damn identity
is maybe it's sex for you and it's
ethnicity for you and it's gender for
you and god only knows what it is for
you and you know and that's who you
identify with and all there is in the
world and this is the post modernist
view is hierarchies of
people in these identity groups
struggling for Dominion you know and
that's a quasi Marxist viewpoint it's
just a variant of the bourgeoisie versus
proletariat theory of history which is a
foolish theory as far as I'm concerned
and certainly not one that we need to
take forward into the 21st century
although we seem you know destined to
insist that we do so he believed that
the revolutionary overthrow of the
oppressor class was necessary and
morally demanded and that turns out to
be a little bloodier than I would say
the typical Christian judeo-christian
ethic might require because it doesn't
require you to take up arms against your
evil overlords and well put them in goo
legs and kill them by the millions for
example and that to me seems to be an
important difference there's there's no
in in the judeo-christian tradition
there's no guilt there's no group guilt
right you're guilty and you're guilty of
different things right I presume and and
that's your problem but maybe you're
also innocent who knows you know but
whatever it's on you it's not a
consequence of your racial heritage or
your ethnicity or your gender any of
those things it's it's between you and
God
let's eres between you and the state
even but at least it's between you and
the state or God it's not like well you
know your father was a factory owner
let's say your grandfather and so it was
perfectly reasonable during the Russian
Revolution and the Red Terror to vacuum
you up along with your whole family and
do away with you because you'd be the
irredeemably tainted by your burgeois z
past so that's another place where
Marxism and judeo-christianity
are then they're not just different like
they're opposite you know it's not just
variant one invariant - these are like
seriously different ideas and so there's
another reason you can't be a Marxist in
a Christian as if you and then there's
the idea that
you know that marks had that religion
was the opiate of the masses which
doesn't exactly sound like I've always
thought religion was the opiate of the
masses but communism Marxism was the
methamphetamine of the of the masses
let's say yeah the meth of the masses we
we had no idea with regards to opiates
so here's what Marx has to say about
religion the abolition of religion as
the illusory happiness of the people is
the demand for the real happiness to
call on them to give up their illusions
about their condition is to call on them
to give up a condition that requires
illusions it's interesting to me because
it's not like the judeo-christian story
was really a happy one as far as far as
I can tell you know I mean there was
heaven but Genesis II you were gonna get
in man that was low and and and mostly
it was a fair bit of original sin you
know and a fair bit of you wrestling
with all of your inadequacies and your
proclivity towards malevolence to pick
up your cross to bear your suffering to
understand that you know there is a war
in your soul between the forces of good
and evil it's like how that's an opiate
is beyond me I mean if I was going to
design an opiate that made people feel
better I'd certainly dispense with a
fair bit of that it's like whatever you
do is okay we could start with that
there's certainly no hell that's
something we're gonna get rid of right
away little less guilt and shame would
be it could be like a hippie cult in the
1960s you know with a little more
marijuana and some free sex something
something like that so I don't really
understand the illusion idea there is
Marxist criticism I suppose of the
belief of you know the great the Great
Father in the sky hoo-hoo-hoo still
doesn't seem to me to be that like he's
sort of still kind of a nightmarish
creature all things considered since at
least in principle he's keeping track of
everything you do even more than you are
and that's not such a good thing but
whatever so it's a foolish criticism as
far as I can tell it doesn't matter he's
still criticized it the criticism of
religion is therefore in
Brio the criticism of that veil of tears
of which religion is the halo criticism
meaning his has plucked the imaginary
flowers on the chain not in order that
man shall continue to bear that chain
without fantasy or consolation but so
that he shall throw off the chain and
pluck the living flower that's something
that plenty of Marxists did I can tell
you the criticism of religion
disillusions man so that he will think
act and fashion his reality like a man
who has discarded his illusions and
regained his senses so that he will move
around himself as his own true son s UN
yeah well that's that's Marxism in a
nutshell all right I mean that's like
that's the fundamental definition of
pathological merit narcissism so that he
will move around himself as his own true
son right religion is only the illusory
son which revolves around man as long as
he does not revolve around himself and
you know generally we don't use that as
an insult
he only revolves around himself isn't
that an insult and isn't this the reason
for that don't we assume that there's
something that you should be revolving
around that isn't just yourself you know
it's it's it's it could be many things
you know it could be while someone you
love that that would be a start could be
a child could be your your partner in
life it could be it could be your family
in extension could be your community it
could be some noble ideal that you're
trying to serve should be something
other than you as the primary center of
the universe around which well you and
presumably everything else revolves so I
don't really see that as a particularly
wise what would you call it philosophy
and as it manifested itself in the world
you know I would say Stalin probably
revolved around himself quite nicely
since and don't you think I mean if you
had to pick someone who was revolving
around himself it would be a pretty
decent competition between Mao and
Stalin and-and-and that didn't seem to
be that didn't seem to be for the best
so so that's something to consider as
well
the Marxists believed that religion
hindered human development and the
Soviets and the Maoists instituted state
atheism apart from the worship of their
leaders of course and then I'm gonna
read you a poem by Marx this is a good
one I found this a while back god it's a
rough poem and you know you want it you
want to let your imagination sort of I
would say let your imagination loose
with with this poem which is what you
should do with the poem and imagine the
sort of state of mind that you have to
be in to write a poem like this and then
also imagine as you should that poetry
like dreams are the birth its birthplace
of thought with my undergraduates often
especially ones that are really obsessed
with ideas they'll often put really bad
poetry in their essays and and I'm not
saying that in a in a cynical way
because bad poetry can have good ideas
in it it's it's hard to write good
poetry you know but the thing is often
an idea that's extraordinarily emotional
in content will manifest itself as a
poem before it is able to articulate
itself out into a fully expressed
philosophy and so I see this with my
undergraduates they'll really be
obsessed with something that's bothering
them then the rights of some poem often
about a personal experience and then as
I help them shape the essay they kind of
unfold the poem into an articulated
statement about the structure of reality
and so you could say well you know we're
all embedded in the dream we know that
you go to sleep every night and you
dream you're embedded in your
imagination if you're if you're
forbidden to dream if you're deprived of
your dreams you will lose your mind
that's been experimentally demonstrated
quite nicely on animals but also on
human beings you have to dream you have
to enter that that realm of incoherent
imagination and possibility in order to
maintain your sanity which is
extraordinarily interesting and very
strange and I would say poetry exists on
the border between the dream and the
fully articulate wakefulness it's it's
it's it's it's the place where the image
of the dream meets the meets the meets
the meets the articulated speech
full consciousness and so you can think
about that with regards to this poem
invocation of one in despair so a God
has snatched from me all my all in the
curse and rack of Destiny all his worlds
are gone beyond recall nothing but
revenge is left to me on my self revenge
I'll proudly wreak on that being that
enthroned Lord make my strength a
patchwork of what's weak leave my better
self without reward I shall build my
throne high overhead cold tremendous
shell its summit be for its bulwark
superstitious dread for its Marshall
blackest agony who looks upon it with a
healthy I shall turn back struck deathly
pale and dumb clutched by blind and
chilled mortality may his happiness
prepare its tomb and the Almighty's
Lightning shall rebound from that
massive Iron Giant if he brings my walls
and towers down eternity shall raise
them up defiant well I would say that's
the sort of poem that would be written
by someone who revolved around himself
as his own true son and I would also say
that given what we know about what
happened as a consequence of the
instantiation of Marxist doctrine that
this is a truly horrifying piece of
literature to contemplate written by the
way when Marx was rather young so then
the question came to me do I believe in
God and I don't like that question
and people have complained at me a lot
and I'm sure they have the reasons
because they don't like my answers you
know and I have two answers they've kind
of become stalk which is not a good
thing but but they're the best
approximate exactly I've got three I had
three sort of burgeoning hypotheses one
was it's none of your damn business
that's the first one so it's like a
privacy issue like it seemed to me to be
a question that was too private to be
answered properly and so and you know
you could consider that a cop-out and
maybe it is and then another one was
well what do you mean by believe like do
you mean the words do you mean to say
the words I believe in God does that
indicate that you believe in God like I
don't know what you mean by believe
exactly because and that's got me in
trouble too because you know people
think that attempting to clarify the
meaning of words is an attempt to escape
from the question when it's actually an
attempt to specify the question I mean
is what you believe what you say or what
you act out now you know I would say to
some degree it's both but if push comes
to shove as far as I'm concerned what
you believe is what you act out not what
you say and then you know and if you're
an integrated person then what you act
out and what you say are the same thing
and then you're a person whose word can
be trusted right because what you say
and what you do are isomorphic they're
the same thing but belief is
instantiated in action so I have also
suggested that I act as if I believe in
God or to the best of my ability and
people aren't very happy with that
either but and then the third is that
I'm afraid that he might exist which i
think is the most comical of the three
answers and perhaps the most accurate
one but then but then I was thinking
about this today when I was thinking
about what I might talk to you guys
about and I thought well let's go into
this a little bit more let's say you say
you do believe in God
say I believe in God it's like okay well
that's hypothetically pretty impressive
I would say it's like you believe that
there's a divine power that oversees
everything that is fundamentally ethical
that's watching everything you do and
and you believe that and so what effect
does that have on your behavior if you
believe it does that mean that you're
well are you --fill are you all-in on
your beliefs are you sacrificing
everything to this transcendent entity
that you proclaim belief in have you
cleansed yourself of all your sin let's
say are you making all the sacrifices
that you need to make like have you
taken the mote out of your I know or or
or or are you in the same situation
let's say that the Catholic Church seems
to be in right now just out of curiosity
bring that up since the Pope seems to be
concerned with what's been happening
with the Catholic Church given the
endless pedophilic scandals let's say
which seem rather serious in my
estimation and might have been something
that was cleaned up perhaps a hundred or
a thousand years ago and it's being
taken seriously perhaps now and perhaps
not because it's not so easy to
determine exactly what it would mean to
take that seriously and you might say
well are all the people who are
committing these highness actions and
then covering them up or if you ask them
well do you believe in God what are they
going to say well you'd think the answer
would be yes given that they're like
priests and and yet and yet what's the
evidence well the evidence isn't exactly
so clear that the mere statement let's
say or the mirror acting out of the
ritual let's say and I'm not trying to
denigrate the statement or the ritual
but I'm pointing out that that's no
indication of your right to say that you
believe
because you got it and I think this is
why it's more than me to answer this
question it's like what right do I have
to say that to make that claim I believe
in God well what's the claim is that the
claim that I'm a good person somehow
because you think that if you believed
in God actually like like seriously that
you'd be a good person like right now
because well for obvious reasons I would
think and so if that hasn't happened in
some sort of miraculous sense so that
you're the best person you could
possibly imagine being on an ongoing
basis and then terrified of of deviating
from that path in a serious manner then
I don't see why you have the right to
say that you believe in God you know one
of the things Nietzsche said about
Christianity it was a great critic of
Christianity although also a great
friend in a very peculiar way in that
sometimes your best friend is the one
who points out your weakest properties
let's say he said as far as he was
concerned there was only one Christian
and he died on the cross and and that's
that's a you know perhaps an extreme
statement but one worth giving some
consideration to it's like well then you
look at what if what are you called upon
let's say if you're going to proclaim
yourself as a believer you know and I
thought about this a lot as I've gone
through the Old Testament I did a bunch
of lectures last year and so what do you
called upon well you're called upon
initially to act out the spark of
divinity that's within you by
confronting potential with the logos
that's within you which means to take
the opportunities that are in front of
you the potential future and to
transform it into the present in the
best possible way using truth and
courage and careful articulation as your
as your as your as your as your guide so
that's the first thing you're called on
to do now that's a major deal there
that's a tough one and then the second
is to make the proper sacrifices that's
the Cain and Abel story is like you you
want something you genuinely want it you
want to set the
world straight than you let go of what's
necessary and you pursue you let go of
what isn't necessary no matter what it
is no matter what it is and then you
pursue what's necessary and then maybe
you sacrifice your children to God that
that was the story that's the one of the
next stories that comes up of course and
you think well that's pretty damn
barbaric and the way the story's laid
out of course it is but that isn't
exactly what it means it means that what
you try to do when you raise children is
that you try to do everything you can to
impress upon them by imitation and by
instruction and by love and by
encouragement that they are crucial
beings in the world whose ethical
decisions play an important role in
shaping the structure of reality itself
and that they have the moral
responsibility to do that and you get
your Ark in order that's your family
let's say so that when the storms come
you can stay above water for the 40 days
of flooding and you're capable of
leading your people through the desert
when the desert makes itself manifest
and you can escape from tyranny properly
because you're wise enough to see it and
you take the full burden of being on
yourself all the suffering that's that's
part and parcel of that you accept that
voluntarily let's say and you do
everything you can to confront the
malevolence that's part of you and
that's part of the state and it's part
of the world and you you you make a
garden around you that's the paradise a
walled garden it's a walled well watered
place so the forces of nature and
society exist together in harmony and
you place your family in that so that
they can live properly and you treat
your enemy as if he's yourself and the
same with your brother and well then you
can say then maybe you can say maybe
then you have the right to say that you
believe in God otherwise maybe you
should think twice about it because you
know there's a line in the New Testament
that Christ Himself says two of them I
should read them two because there are
very relevant to this I guess I could
pair of
Frye's to paraphrase them a rich man
comes up to Christ and says and and says
good good leader good lord and he asked
him a question about how it is that he
should be a good person and Christ says
don't call me good there's no one that's
good but God and you know that's worth
thinking about I mean the one person
that in principle in our ancient stories
had the right to make some direct
connection between himself and the
divine was unwilling to do it when
challenged and so it might be reasonable
to assume that each of us could be much
more cautious about making that sort of
statement bluntly when we're asked and
then the other line is not all those who
say Lord Lord will enter the kingdom of
heaven got that about right
which means something approximating just
because you make a claim to moral virtue
let's say your belief in God which I
can't see how you can make a higher
claim to moral virtue than that you know
I mean agnostic atheistic I don't recap
the purpose the point is something like
this imagine something of ultimate
transcendent value I don't care whether
you believe in it or not but imagine
that something like that exists and then
you swear allegiance to it which is to
say I believe in this I mean there's a
heavy moral burden that comes along with
that just to allow yourself to utter the
words without feeling that you should be
immediately struck down appropriately by
lightning and so well and so I think
that's why that question makes me
uncomfortable it's that I don't think I
have a I don't think I have a right to
make that Proclamation there's another
thing too that I learned when I was
going through these biblical lectures it
was a fascinating thing to do was the
story of Jacob who became Israel and
Jacob was a real
you know he was a morally ambiguous
figure to put it mildly and he tricked
his older brother out of his birthright
and he was full of tricks and he had a
lot of tricks played on him too and
maybe learned something as a consequence
anyways after running away from his
brother who had murderous thoughts and
for good reasons for I liked about 20
years maybe it was only 14 but doesn't
matter it was a long time he decided
that he would go back and try to make
peace and he came to this river he sent
his family across the river along with
his belongings um and and partly as an
offering to his brother a peace offering
and he had a dream dream visionary
experience hallucination God who knows
what it was and he dreamt that he
wrestled with an angel all night and
that the angel was God and God he won
which is very strange because well first
of all he was a trickster figure you
know like he wasn't your most upstanding
moral creature he wasn't Noah for
example and second well it was God you
know it's like figure to wrestle with
someone and lose there's an opponent
that's likely to take you out and he did
damage his hip him so what not that
impressive an accomplishment on thoughts
pardon my estimation but but it's a very
interesting story because what it does
indicate what's so cool about it you see
Jacobs name is changed at that point to
Israel and Israel means those who
wrestle with God and then that's so that
blue meal is one of the things I love
about studying old stories is now and
then you come across a piece of one and
you and you see in it into it you know
you see down into the depths that that
characterizes it's very difficult but
happens sometimes and it just flattens
you you know to think that if Israel is
that is the chore if Israel is the
chosen people of God that's the
hypothesis and what Israel means is
those who
wrestle with God then think that that
gives that seems to me to be such a
hopeful idea because well everyone does
that to some degree I mean you do that
in your life because well you don't know
what's a fundamental transcendent worth
you know because who the hell are you
and what do you know you know you're
you're struggling all the time with well
I would say with good and evil when
you're struggling with yourself you're
struggling with the world to to to
portray that as wrestling with God
that's perfectly reasonable from a
metaphoric perspective and the idea that
that's what characterizes the true
people of God is that willingness to
wrestle that's really something because
it kind of indicates that you're here as
a contender you know you're not here to
be happy you're not here to be
complacent you're not here to be
materially satisfied not that that would
be possible anyways but that you're here
to contend with the structure of reality
right and that's what'll satisfy you
because there's something to you you
know you're not weak and nothing there's
something to you there's certainly
something malevolent and terrible I mean
you know that you look at how people
behave you you look at the blood and
catastrophe of our history you can
certainly see though the absolute the
absolute hellish depths of the human
soul but there's there's something that
takes root in that and grows up out of
that it's absolutely magnificent beyond
belief and that's looking for for to
contend you know and I've often thought
that I've been fortunate in my marriage
because you think well you got you get
married and you live happily ever after
it's like
that's not it is it you don't want that
either you know what you putting on it
we want your partner to do just all
she's gonna do is sprinkle rose petals
in front of you right and pat you on the
back of the head and tell you how
wonderful you are constantly day after
day man you'd be so sick of that after -
well maybe take a month but but let's
say two weeks it'd be you you'd be cuz
you know she should be more on the side
of who you could be than on the side of
who you are and if she's deluded enough
or terrified enough to worship you in
your current form then well that doesn't
say much for her and it certainly isn't
very helpful for you you want someone
that's gonna get in the way now and then
you know and and to contend with and
I've been fortunate in my marriage
because I have someone to contend with
you know we we have our our discussions
and they're not easy involved but partly
because we have hard problems to solve
because life is full of hard problems I
want someone who stand up you know and
and have her say even if it's not what I
would say and maybe I'm even willing at
times because she's quite intuitive and
a good dreamer and I'm more facile
verbally and so we have to be careful in
our relationship because if I'm in a
particularly ornery mood and she has
something to say I can usually slice up
her arguments verbally you know and then
that's that's fine as far as I'm
concerned because I get to win but it's
stupid well it's stupid it's first of
all that doesn't mean I'm right it just
means I can formulate verbal arguments
slightly faster than she can but her
intuitions and her dreams are often
extraordinarily accurate and so we've
learned to to some degree to buttress
each other's arguments just on the off
chance that the person that you were
foolish enough to marriage marry might
know something you don't now and then
about something important you know
and so what do you want well you want
someone to contend with and then it's an
adventure you know and then you have
someone that you love and that you
respect and that's not a bad combination
for longevity of relationship and then
maybe if you have someone that you love
and respect and that you can communicate
with and your children also love and
respect her or him and then that's
pretty good for them because they've got
some parents that they could love and
respect that's a good combination you
know it solidifies their life and so you
want to contend with them and you want a
job that's challenging I would say that
pushes you beyond what you already are
and god only knows how much how hard you
need to be pushed in order to go beyond
where you are but you know to some
degree if you have a choice you know
it's not that uncommon that what we'll
do is choose to be pushed to the limit
especially when we're at our best we
think well where's the limit it's here
maybe I can manage that I'm gonna push
myself right to the damn limit then I'm
gonna push myself a little bit over just
to see if it's possible and and if that
happens then you know you emerge with a
sense of of triumph I'm now more than I
was right and maybe that's what you're
here to be is to be more than you were
trying to push those limits and to do
that you contend with the world you
wrestle with God
you don't casually say I believe because
who knows no one no one knows right
we're separated from the infinite by
death and ignorance we don't know we
contend we wrestle you know and in that
maybe we find our destiny at least we
find our purpose we find something
that's that that justifies us to some
degree you know if I'm awake at night
wondering and I thank God you know like
I've I pushed myself as far as I could
in this effort whatever the effort that
I'm considering happens to be I pushed
myself I don't have a weight on my
conscience because I let something go or
I failed to accomplish some I mean I do
often have those sorts of weights I'm
talking about the rare times when I
don't
it's like well there's something that
that that's where there's some atonement
and some peace as far as I'm concerned
where that contending and that wrestling
has been successful and I would say that
insofar as you're deeply involved in
that like completely involved in that
thoroughly involved in that then you
have the right to say that you believe
in God and since I'm not like that
a hundred percent of the time or even
approximating the percent of the time
that I would like to be like that you
know despite my best efforts then when
people ask me I'm not going to say
something virtuous like I'm a believer
because there's plenty wrong with me
that needs to be fixed before I would
dare utter words like that thank you
[Applause]
well so that's better answer to that
question so thank you very much for for
walking through that with me let's say
now you have all not all many of you
have asked some questions tonight using
this nifty little device called slide Oh
which I really like and so now what I'm
going to do is spend 20 minutes or so
looking through the questions that you
asked and seeing if I have anything that
isn't completely incomprehensible and
embarrassing to say about them so let's
try that hmm
well this is a strange one I don't know
about you people from Sydney so uh it's
from Kathy Newman
which strikes me as somewhat unlikely
and it's got a hundred and sixty-four up
votes so which is quite a few up votes
it hurt when you destroyed me on ABC now
I don't know if that's referring to last
night or so many months ago but I have
enrolled in university to get my facts
right
yeah well that probably won't work thank
you for enlightening my soul the burns
are still healing
yeah well that's it's not exactly a
question it's it's it's four sentences
that are quite the strange combination
that I would say something about the
burns are still healing you know I mean
Nietzsche said that you could tell much
about a man's character by how much
truth he could tolerate which is very
interesting you know there's not an idea
in in in the in the great western
tradition that the truth is the way and
the path of life and and that no one
comes to the Father except through the
truth and and I believe that to be the
case because I don't think that you can
manifest who you are without the truth
and so I think it's it's it's literally
and metaphorically truth that the the
pathway to who you could be if you were
completely who you were is through the
truth and I would say and so the truth
does set you free but the problem is is
that it destroys everything that isn't
worthy in you as it sets you free and
that's that's a process of burning and
and and it's it's painful because you
cling to what you shouldn't be partly
out of pride and partly out of ignorance
and partly out of laziness and and and
so then you encounter something true and
you all know this you all know this
well because when was the last time that
you learned something important that
wasn't a blow of some sort you know it's
often you look back at your life and you
think oh god I really learned something
there I wouldn't want to do that again
but it really changed my life I mean
sometimes it can really destroy you you
know an encounter with the truth and you
never really recover but now and then
something comes along and straightens
you out and a lot of you has to go a law
to you has to burn away you know and and
and I suppose in some sense the idea is
that everything about you that isn't
worthy is to be put into the flames and
that's that's another reason to be not
so casual about claiming what you
believe because it isn't something that
you undertake with oh do caution you
know I learned when I was kid about 25
or so little older than a kid that
almost everything that I said was one
form of lie or another and I wasn't any
worse I would say that the people that I
was associating with or any better and
and the lies were manifold you know they
were attempts to win arguments for the
sake of winning the argument that might
be one attempts to indicate my
intellectual prowess when there were
competitions of that sort maybe just the
the sheer pleasure of engaging in an
intact intellectual argument and winning
my inability to distinguish between
ideas that I had read and and
incorporated because I had read but had
realized that I hadn't yet earned the
right to use all of that and you know I
had this experience that lasted a long
time while I would say it's really never
gone away that and I think this was the
awakening of my conscience essentially
and I didn't realize that this until
much later when I was reading Socrates
apology this this voice for lack of a
better
made itself manifest inside me and it
said every time I said something that
wasn't true and that's usually what it
said that's not true you don't believe
that or there was a sensation that was
associated with it I don't think this is
that uncommon you know I asked my
psychology classes for many years in a
row if they hadn't experienced this
experience that they had a voice in
their head let's say it's a metaphor or
a feeling that communicated to them when
they were about to do something wrong
and it was universally the case that
people agreed with one of those
statements or another and the other
thing I would ask is well do you always
listen to it and of course the answer to
that was definitely no but that's also
very interesting you know that you can
have this faculty this conscience this
seems to to me to be very tightly
associated with the idea of free will is
that you can have this internal voice
this Damon
the root word for democracy oh yes I
didn't finish that story so the yes well
it's important well so Socrates Damon
told him it was his moral guide and
democracy appears to be predicated on
the idea that the polity will function
if people attend to their consciousness
that's the that's the that's the overlap
of those conceptualizations and that's
that that's it well first of all I think
that's the case you know and it makes a
certain amount of logical sense I mean
if we assume that the political state is
something like the emergent consequence
of the decisions of all its citizens we
would assume that the wiser the
decisions of the citizens the more
upright and functional the state I can't
see how it could be any other way
and perhaps those who are the most
upright who listen to their
consciousness consciences more carefully
even play a disproportionately powerful
role it's certainly possible so
anyways back to truth well you know I
learned that so much of what I was doing
was false and I think I learned this CIA
there was a reason that this came to me
so clearly I was trying to understand
why people did terrible things and I was
really concentrating on the terrible
terrible things that people do and I was
interested in Auschwitz for example and
Nora now known as a political phenomenon
but as a as a psychological phenomena I
was curious about how you could be a
nosh wits guard and I wasn't really
curious about how you could be one
because well you could be whatnot of
course I was more curious about how I
could be one being such a good person as
I thought I was and but I also knew that
people many people did many terrible
things during the 20th century and the
idea that I was somehow better than them
or that I should assume a priori that I
was better than them and that I wouldn't
have made the same choices or worse had
I been in the same situation was a very
very very dangerous supposition and in
fact a sufficiently dangerous
supposition to bring about the very
danger that I assumed was worth avoiding
I had this idea you know that what had
happened especially in Nazi Germany but
also in in the Soviet Union shouldn't
happen again that what we needed to do
because of what happened in the 20th
century especially because we also
managed to create hydrogen bombs that it
was in that and that we had become so
technologically powerful that it would
there wasn't time for that anymore that
time for that was over and that we
really needed to understand why it
happened and that perhaps we could go
deep enough in that understanding which
is I think what happens when you go deep
and understanding so that you could stop
it because if you if you understand the
problem maybe you can solve it you know
and and
at least in part I came to believe that
the problem was as Solzhenitsyn said
that the problem is is that the line
between good and evil runs down every
human heart and I'd was reading young at
the same time you know and he believed
that the human soul was a tree whose
roots grew all the way to hell and
believed also that in the full
investigation of the shadow which was
the dark side of the human psyche was
that it was bottomless essentially that
that that it was like an experience of
Hell and that also struck me as true and
that the way to stop those sorts of
things from happening was to stop
yourself from being the sort of person
who would do it who would even start to
do it because the other thing you learn
when you learn about atrocities of that
sort you could read ordinary men by the
way which is an unbelievably great study
of exactly this sort of phenomena it's
on my book list on my website it's about
a group of German policemen who were
turned into brutal murderers over a
period of months when they went behind
when they went into Poland after the
Germans had marched - and they were just
ordinary middle-class men and they
weren't forced into this by their
leadership by the way either which was
one of the things that makes the book so
interesting so for me it was a matter of
understanding that if we want this sort
of thing to not happen anymore then we
have to start to become the sort of
people who wouldn't do it
which seems rather self-evident all
things considered unless you know you
believe that were the pawns of social
forces for example like the Marxists do
and I don't believe that because we're
also the creator of social forces and
we're also capable of standing up to
social forces because I would say the
individual is more powerful than the
social force all things considered
interestingly enough that the way to
stop such things - from happening the
way to remember properly is to
understand that that you could do it
that you could do those terrible things
because the people who did them were
like you and that the way out of that is
to stop being like that and the way you
stop being like that is well at least in
part by stop by ceasing to tell yourself
lies that you don't believe in and that
you know you shouldn't act out and you
know and that's made a huge difference
in my life for better for worse I mean
it was very uncanny experience I would
say because it's very discombobulating
to experience yourself as fragmented
enough so that much of what you do and
say is actually false it's a lot of work
to clean that up a lot but the
consequences are in principle worthwhile
and so that was part of what
understanding that was part of what
drove me towards clinical psychology
saying away from political science and
law and from politics in general because
I started to believe that and I think
this is the great Western idea which
people were quite irritated about by the
way on Q&A last night as well that the
proper route forward for the redemption
of the individual and for mankind as a
whole is as a consequence of the
redemption of each individual and I
truly believe that and I believe that
that occurs as a consequence of
adherence to the truth and courage in
the face of being that's rule one right
to stand up straight with your shoulders
back is to take on the onslaught and to
enter the contentious ring and to do
your to do and to do more than your best
because your best isn't enough because
your best isn't as good as you could be
you have to push yourself past that
and and that's as far as I can tell
where you find what you need in life you
find the meaning that sustains you in
life and you find the patterns of action
that redeem the world both at the same
time I mean life is a very difficult
business you know it's it's fatal and
it's full of suffering and it's and it's
full of betrayal and malevolence there's
nothing about it that's trivial
it's all profound and in order to find
your way through all of that that that
capacity for hellish experience let's
say you need to develop a relationship
with something that's profound
and you can you have that capacity and
what could be more profound than the
truth and what would you rather have on
your side and you might say well that's
obvious and of course everyone should do
that and then you need to know why you
don't and the answer is well it sort of
encapsulated in this first amusing
question you don't thank you for
enlightening my soul the burns are still
healing it's like well you know there's
no shortage of Deadwood to burn off and
and there's no shortage of pain when the
deadwood burns off and that's what makes
people afraid of the truth you know
maybe that's why Moses encountered God
in the burning bush who the hell knows
but there's something about that idea
that seems to me to be the case and so
what's the decision that you make you
know you decide to believe you know it's
a risk an existential risk it's an
active faith you believe that the truth
can set you free you believe that people
have an intrinsic divinity about their
soul you decide that you're going to
live in that manner and that you're
going to let everything about yourself
that isn't worthy of that goal die and
that might be almost every
that you are and that's a terrible thing
to contemplate the only thing that's
worse I would say is the alternative
because the alternative is the sorts of
hell's that we managed to produce around
us and that we produced with particular
expertise during the totalitarian
regimes of the 20th century and it would
be a good thing if we decided
collectively and individually not to go
back there again thank you
you